Guide to the Bass Family Papers 1864-1959
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Bass Family Papers
1864-1959
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 196
Bass family
8 reels microfilm
This collection contains the diaries of Virginia E. Bass; various legal documents and financial records for the Bass family enterprises; speeches and writings pertinent to the Stevensville, Montana area; a small collection of correspondence; newspaper clippings; and photographs.
Location of originals unknown.
Biographical Note
Dudley C. Bass, born in 1842, and his brother William E. Bass, born 1838, were natives of Vermont, the sons of William B. Bass and Ruth (Childs) Bass. They moved to Montana's Bitterroot Valley in 1864, where they first concentrated on mining. They began raising hay, grain, and fruit, which they sold in the mining camps. In 1871 the brothers started the first orchard, the Pine Grove Fruit Farm, on their 320-acre plot of land in Stevensville, Montana. The business prospered, propelling the brothers to expand their land holdings to 1000 acres and increase the variety of produce they planted. They not only distributed their produce to the surrounding areas but also shipped it to many cities along the Atlantic Coast and even some of the lower Canadian states. They also raised Durham cattle, Norman-Percheron horses, and choice breeds of sheep. The Bass brothers also endeavored in a sawmill, a grist mill, and ran a freight line between the Bitterroot and Corrine, Utah.
William E. Bass made his name not only as a prominent entrepreneur but he also served four terms on the Territorial Council, including one as its president in 1877. He also served three terms as a member of the Montana Legislature.
Virginia E. Bass, William's wife, was only the second white woman to live in Stevensville, arriving in 1864. Virginia's sister, Etta Emmett, joined her some years later and subsequently married Dudley Bass; they had one son, Lee Emmett. The Bass family was held in such high esteem in the Bitterroot Valley that Bass Peak, Bass Creek, Bass Canyon, and Bass Crossing were all named for them.
This collection contains the diaries of Virginia E. Bass for 1871 through 1922. Also present are various legal documents, financial records for the brother's mining, agricultural, and business enterprises such as inventory lists of the livestock and equipment on several of their properties, deeds, and shareholding certificates. Speeches and writings pertinent to the Stevensville, Montana area are also a part of this series. This collection also contains a few letters written by Etta Bass to her husband Dudley, newspaper clippings pertinent to the history of the Bitterroot Valley, and photographs of the Bass family holdings and the Stevensville, Montana, area.
The collection is divided into seven series:
Series I: The Diaries of Virginia E. Bass, 1891-1922, 1971
Series II: Correspondence, 1884
Series III: Financial Records, 1877-1908
Series IV: Legal Documents, 1876-1895
Series V: Speeches and Writings, 1908
Series VI: Clippings, 1903-1913
Series VII: Photographs, 13 photographs, 1869-1915
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
The materials in this collection remained with the Bass family until they were loaned to the K. Ross Toole Archives for microfilming.
The Bass family papers were loaned for microfilming by Lee Bass in 1968 and by Lucille Bass in 1976. Lucille Bass also donated the photographs in 1976.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Business records--Montana--Stevensville; Clippings --Montana--Stevensville; Diaries--Montana--Stevensville; Family papers--Montana--Stevensville; Financial records--Montana--Stevensville; Legal documents--Montana--Stevensville; Photographs--Montana--Stevensville; Speeches, addresses, etc., American--Montana--Stevensville
Agriculture--Montana--Stevensville; Gristmills--Montana--Stevensville; Women--Montana--Stevensville --Correspondence; Women--Montana--Stevensville--Diaries
Bitterroot River Valley--History; Stevensville (Mont.)--Social life and customs
Bass family
Bass, Dudley C., b. 1842; Bass, Etta; Bass, Virginia E.; Bass, William E., b. 1838
Montana; Diaries; Labor History; City and Town Life; Women
- The Diaries of Virginia E. Bass, 1871-1922; Series I; 31 frames on 1 microfilm reel 5 microfilm reels
  This series includes the daily accounts of Virginia Bass's life in Stevensville, Montana from 1871 to 1922. Reel 1 includes material that is duplicated on Reel 2. She recounts the weather faithfully, and also includes many details of daily life: growing and harvesting food, raising livestock, people and visitors, family life, visits to the doctor, church and social groups, and some current and world events. The 1922 diary leaves off at January 16. The other diaries, particularly 1895, have many blank pages.
  - 1871-1874 (Reel-frame 1/305-329)
  - 18711874 (Reel-frame 2/2-26)
  - 1890-1891 (Reel-frame 2/27-125)
  - 1892 (Reel-frame 2/126-222)
  - 1893 (Reel-frame 2/223-315)
  - 1894 (Reel-frame 2/316-413)
  - 1895 (Reel-frame 2/414-509)
  - 1897 (Reel-frame 2/510-694)
  - 1898-1899 (Reel-frame 2/695-1066)
  - 1900 (Reel-frame 2/1067)
  - 1901 (Reel-frame 3/1-191)
  - 1902 (Reel-frame 3/192-382)
  - 1903 (Reel-frame 3/383-579)
  - 1904 (Reel-frame 3/580-642)
  - 1905 (Reel-frame 3/643-829)
  - 1906 (Reel-frame 3/830)
  - 1907 (Reel-frame 4/1-184)
  - 1908 (Reel-frame 4/185-368)
  - 1909 (Reel-frame 4/369-554)
  - 1910 (Reel-frame 4/555-739)
  - 1911 (Reel-frame 4/740-926)
  - 1912 (Reel-frame 4/927)
  - 1913 (Reel-frame 5/1-184)
  - 1914 (Reel-frame 5/185-371)
  - 1915 (Reel-frame 5/372-543)
  - 1916 (Reel-frame 5/544-727)
  - 1917 (Reel-frame 5/728-913)
  - 1918 (Reel-frame 5/914)
  - 1919 (Reel-frame 6/1-178)
  - 1920 (Reel-frame 6/179-364)
  - 1921 (Reel-frame 6/365-485)
  - 1922 (Reel-frame 6/486)
- Correspondence, 1884-1921; Series II; 6 frames on 1 microfilm reel 7 frames on 1 microfilm reel
  This series includes a letter from Etta Bass to assert her legal right to make decisions concerning the property owned by she and her husband Dudley Bass. It also contains a similar letter from Virginia Bass concerning her legal rights of property owned by she and her husband, William Bass.
  - Etta E. Bass, 1884 (Reel-frame 1/238-240)
  - Virginia E. Bass, 1884 (Reel-frame 1/241-243)
  - Correspondence, 1892-1921 (Reel-frame 6/496-503)
- Financial Records, 1864-1909; Series III; 86 frames on 1 reel microfilm 550 frames on 2 reels microfilm
  These papers contain the account ledger for the Bass brothers' gristmill from 1873-1875 and 1882. This collection also includes mortgages from 1879-1882, 1884, 1886, 1889-1890, and 1893 and promissory notes for the years 1877, 1881-1884, 1886-1889, and 1893. These documents comprise the bulk of this series but a small section of records for various leases (1881), a grant record (1890), stock certificates for Stevensville Hotel Company (1895) and Stevensville Real Estate and Loan Company (1890) are present. Various letters written in 1908 regarding the financial concerns of the Bass brothers also have a small holding within this series. A ledger dating 1864-1866 relates to the Bass brother's mining ventures and shows egg and butter sales. The ledger from Chatfield & Bass contains appears to be that of a dry goods or general merchandise operation and contains the names of many prominent Bitterroot Valley residents. The 1887-1900 ledger appears to be that of the Bass produce business and records sales of livestock, meat, apples (varieties are listed), apple cier, berries, plums, tomatoes, and strawberry plants. A group of miscellaneous financial documents on Reel 7 are duplicated on Reel 1.
  - Ledger, 1864-1866 (Reel-frame 6/504-535)
  - 1873 (Reel-frame 1/253-262, 264, 266-283)
  - Gristmill ledgers, 1874 (Reel-frame 1/260-263, 265, 269-270, 284-297)
  - Gristmill ledgers, 1875 (Reel-frame 1/298)
  - Gristmill ledgers, 1882 (Reel-frame 1/299-303)
  - Ledger, Chatfield & Bass, 1881-1883 (Reel-frame 6/536, 7/1-62)
  - Ledger, 1889 (Reel-frame 7/63-168)
  - Ledger, 1887-1900 (Reel-frame 7/169-312)
  - Ledger, 1895-1909 (Reel-frame 7/313-500)
  - Mortgages, 1880 (Reel-frame 1/39, 45)
  - Mortgages, 1881 (Reel-frame 1/51, 68)
  - Mortgages, 1882 (Reel-frame 1/78, 83, 105, 111)
  - Mortgages, 1884 (Reel-frame 1/138)
  - Mortgages, 1886 (Reel-frame 1/155)
  - Mortgages, 1889 (Reel-frame 1/200)
  - Mortgages, 1890 (Reel-frame 1/213)
  - Mortgages, 1893 (Reel-frame 1/230)
  - Mortgages, 1894 (Reel-frame 1/235)
  - Promissory Notes, 1877 (Reel-frame 1/9)
  - Promissory Notes, 1881 (Reel-frame 1/74)
  - Promissory Notes, 1883 (Reel-frame 1/121)
  - Promissory Notes, 1883 (Reel-frame 1/131)
  - Promissory Notes, 1884 (Reel-frame 1/142)
  - Promissory Notes, 1887 (Reel-frame 1/161)
  - Promissory Notes, 1887 (Reel-frame 1/188)
  - Promissory Notes, 1888 (Reel-frame 1/199)
  - Promissory Notes, 1889 (Reel-frame 1/212)
  - Promissory Notes, 1893 (Reel-frame 1/235)
  - Leases, 1881 (Reel-frame 1/57)
  - Grants, 1890 (Reel-frame 1/202-203)
  - Stock Holdings, Stevensville Hotel Company, undated (Reel-frame 1/248)
  - Stock Holdings, Stevensville Real Estate & Loan Association, undated (Reel-frame 1/249)
  - Financial Letters, 1908 (Reel-frame 1/250)
  - Miscellaneous financial, 1881-1897 (Reel-frame 7/500)
- Legal Documents, 1866-1959; Series IV; 216 frames of 1 microfilm reel 330 frames on 2 microfilm reels
  This series consists of deeds to various properties owned by the Bass brothers in the years spanning from 1880-1895. Indentures are also present in the collection for the years of 1878 through 1891 and 1893. These two sections comprise the bulk of the legal documents, but there are some U.S. Land Office documents (1876, 1883, & 1888) and executions of sale of real estate from the Sheriff's office (1889-1890) present. A Sheriff's deed under foreclosure issued in 1895 and a court summons for the Bass brothers for 1893 are also listed. Several portions of Reel 7 and 8 duplicate materials on Reel 1. Mining materials on Reel 8 document the Bass brother's involvement with the Lawyers Combination Lode mining claim in Missoula County and the Log Cabin Quartz Lode mining claim. There is considerable correspondence with R.P. Anderson of Lolo, Montana, regarding this. There is also a stock certificate from the Bonanza Mountain Copper Company. Bass house materials from 1909 document the costs and skilled labor involved in the construction of a new Bass residence.
  - Legal, 1866-1882 (Reel-frame 7/518-616)
  - Legal, 1883-1889 (Reel-frame 7/617, 8/1-57)
  - Legal, 1890-1898 (Reel-frame 8/58-96)
  - Legal, 1900-1959 (Reel-frame 8/97-216)
  - Deeds, 1880 (Reel-frame 1/24-27, 31-34)
  - Deeds, 1881 (Reel-frame 1/61, 65, 75)
  - Deeds, 1882 (Reel-frame 1/92, 96, 117)
  - Deeds, 1883 (Reel-frame 1/122, 126)
  - Deeds, 1884 (Reel-frame 1/132, 135)
  - Deeds, 1885 (Reel-frame 1/142, 145-151)
  - Deeds, 1886 (Reel-frame 1/158, 161)
  - Deeds, 1887 (Reel-frame 1/166, 169, 171, 174, 177, 184)
  - Deeds, 1888 (Reel-frame 1/189, 191, 194)
  - Deeds, 1889 (Reel-frame 1/204, 209)
  - Deeds, 1890 (Reel-frame 1/217, 220)
  - Indentures, 1877 (Reel-frame 1/10-13)
  - Indentures, 1878 (Reel-frame 1/76-77)
  - Indentures, 1879 (Reel-frame 1/5-6, 14-20)
  - Indentures, 1880 (Reel-frame 1/21-23, 28-30, 35-38, 40-44, 46-20, 66-67)
  - Indentures, 1881 (Reel-frame 1/52-56, 58-60, 62-64, 69-73)
  - Indentures, 1882 (Reel-frame 1/79-82, 84-91, 93-95, 97-104, 106-120)
  - Indentures, 1883 (Reel-frame 1/123-125, 127-129)
  - Indentures, 1884 (Reel-frame 1/133-134, 136-137, 139-141)
  - Indentures, 1885 (Reel-frame 1/143-144, 146)
  - Indentures, 1886 (Reel-frame 1/152-154, 156-157, 159-160)
  - Indentures, 1887 (Reel-frame 1/162-165, 167-168, 170, 172-173, 175-176, 178-183, 185-187)
  - Indentures, 1888 (Reel-frame 1/189-190, 192-193, 195-196, 198-199)
  - Indentures, 1889 (Reel-frame 1/201, 205, 210-211, 214)
  - Indentures, 1890 (Reel-frame 1/218-219, 221-222)
  - Indentures, 1891 (Reel-frame 1/223-226)
  - Indentures, 1893 (Reel-frame 1/231-234, 236-237)
  - Mining, 1886-1942 (Reel-frame 8/217-276)
  - U.S. Land Office Documents, 1876 (Reel-frame 1/7-8)
  - U.S. Land Office Documents, 1883 (Reel-frame 1/130)
  - U.S. Land Office Documents, 1888 (Reel-frame 1/197)
  - Sheriff's Execution of Sales, 1889 (Reel-frame 1/206-208)
  - Sheriff's Execution of Sales, 1890 (Reel-frame 1/215-216)
  - Notice of Foreclosure, 1895 (Reel-frame 1/244-247)
  - Court Summons, undated (Reel-frame 1/227-229)
  - Bass house contracts, 1909 (Reel-frame 8/277)
- Speeches and Writings, 1908 and undated; Series V; 2 frames on 1 reel of microfilm 11 frames on 1 reel of microfilm
  This small section contains letters written on various subjects from the year 1908 and an undated memoir of early life and development of the Bitterroot Valley by an unknown author.
  - Letters, 1908 (Reel-frame 1/251)
  - Memoir fragment, undated (Reel-frame 8/300-311)
- Clippings, 1903-1913; Series VI; 1 frame of 1 reel of microfilm
  This series contains newspaper clippings from the Stevensville Register and the Northwest Tribune on the early settlement and history of the Bitterroot Valley. Materials are duplicated on both Reel 1 and Reel 8.
  - Newspaper clipping, Stevensville Register: (V.1, No 5?), 1903-08-26 (Reel-frame 1/330, Reel-frame 8/312)
  - Newspaper clipping, Stevensville Register: (V. 8, No. 17), 1909-12-23 (Reel-frame 1/330, Reel-frame 8/312)
  - Newspaper clipping, Stevensville Register: (V. 11, No. 22), 1913-01-09 (Reel-frame 1/330, Reel-frame 8/312)
  - Newspaper clipping, Stevensville Register: (V. 10, No.33), 1912-09-14 (Reel-frame 1/330, Reel-frame 8/312)
  - Newspaper clipping, Northwest Tribune: (V. 26 No. 33), 1912-11-01 (Reel-frame 1/330, Reel-frame 8/312)
- Photographs, 1869-1915; Series VII; Thirteen photographs
  This series contains photographs documenting the Bass family, their business holdings, and development of the Bitterroot Valley. There are several images of Stevensville, and others of Native Americans in the area.
  - H. Fevencamp and two others on trail with pack horses [on hunting expedition], undated; 76-43
  - First steam-powered sawmill in the Bitterroot Valley, located near Florence, Montana, on One Horse Creek., 1886; 76-44
    At this time the mill was owned by the Bass family.
  - Wedding party of Lee and Lucille Bass posed next to the Bass family home, Stevensville, Montana, 1915; 76-45
  - Building along Third Street, Stevensville, Montana, ca. 1910; 76-46
  - Old Bass ranch, Pine Grove Ranch, Bass family posed in front. Left to right: Mrs. and Mrs. Dudley Bass, Lucille Bass, Virginia Bass, Lee Bass, ca. 1915; 76-47
  - Tipis pitched on Fort Owen field northwest of Bass family home, ca. 1912; 76-48
  - Main Street, Stevensville, Montana, ca. 1910; 76-49
  - Main Street, after snow storm, Stevensville, Montana, March 17, 1910; 76-50
  - Mr. and Mrs. Dudley Bass and Virginia Bass (in black skirt and hat) eating picnic lunch, ca. 1910; 76-51
  - Stevensville Hotel, Stevensville, Montana, ca. 1910; 76-52
  - Bass School on Bass Creek, northwest of Stevensville, Montana, 1906; 76-53
    Boy in back row next to teacher is Lee Bass.
  - Mission at Stevensville, Montana, ca. 1891; 76-54
    This photo was taken in front of the old mission at Stevensville, Montana, at the time when General Carrington negotiated the final treaty removing the Flathead Indians to the Jocko Valley.
  - House of Representatives, Helena, Montana, ca. 1910; 76-55
  - Letterhead of Bonner and Welch Mercantile, 1869; 76-56
    Predecessor of Missoula Mercantile, Missoula, Montana.